[groovy guitar music]
♪ ♪
[fans whooshing]
[air whooshing]
[eerie music]
♪ ♪
[sniffs]
[inhales sharply]
♪ ♪
No.
Sweetie. stay with me.
Mom. my stomach hurts.
Mine too.
This'll all be over soon.
[door clicks]
[tense music]
♪ ♪
[grunts]
Don't be scared.
Mommy's gonna fix everything.
Please. it's been days.
Have you made your choice?
He needs to eat.
[breathes deeply]
♪ ♪
Yes.
So you're saying
that this car is tied
to a missing person's case?
What?
A mother and young son
disappeared
when they were visiting
family upstate.
FBI is assisting in the search.
but this is the first
real lead we've gotten.
The plates are a match
to the Palmers'.
Well. wherever they went.
they left their luggage behind.
Park ranger found it a few
days ago abandoned by a trail.
I just got around to logging
the plates in this morning.
You've been sitting on
the information for 48 hours?
That's the two
of them there. OK?
And every second counts.
so if there's anything else
you might have overlooked...
Like I told you.
the car was abandoned.
We towed it.
- Heads up.
Got a vertical gash
on the sidewall of this flat.
It's about two inches long.
Any chance they just hit a curb?
No. I don't think so.
This kerf is deep and narrow.
and there's no radial scuffing.
Somebody slashed it.
We need the exact location
where this was towed from.
♪ ♪
I'm Agent Bell.
This is Agent Ramos and Scola.
SUV was over this way.
Tire was flat. so I cut
whoever owned it some slack.
gave him time to find a spare.
- When was this?
Thursday.
After a couple days.
I called for a tow.
A man's gotta have limits
to his goodwill.
Mr. Bream. do you think
it's possible that the Palmers
got lost on the trail?
Over the years.
some folks have been known
to go in and never come out.
What does that mean?
Nature can be cruel. that's all.
You said you were
working that day.
You see these people?
No. not that I recall.
Any cameras in the park?
Not unless you're looking
for Hessel's hairstreak.
What?
It's a butterfly on
the endangered species list.
Beautiful creature.
They're dying off.
Ah. suppose some things are
too fragile for this world.
Hanford University put up this
camera last year to track 'em.
Pretty sure that it records.
[soft dramatic music]
All right. we're gonna need
to get our hands
on that footage.
And while you're at it.
a list of your whereabouts
this past week.
♪ ♪
We finally caught a break
in our missing person's case.
We now know that
Valerie and Troy Palmer
detoured on their way
from Long Island to Utica.
We located their vehicle here.
tires slashed.
seemingly abandoned.
But maybe they went hiking
and got lost or hurt.
although something tells me
that tire didn't slash itself.
Either way. we are swimming
with questions.
and we need to start
fishing for answers. Yeah.
State police expanded
the search grid
to include the trail.
No trace of the family.
- But?
They found Valerie Palmer's
cell phone in a ditch.
smashed pretty good.
- [sighs]
I do not like
where this is going.
Hey. got that butterfly
cam video cued
to the day
the Palmers went missing.
Let her rip.
OK. here they are.
Mother and son stopping
for a hike. right?
Tire looks fine.
Scrub forward.
Whoa. whoa. whoa.
Who is this?
[tense music]
Whoa.
That explains the tire.
Think that's enough for an ID?
Got a little profile there.
- Maybe.
- What about the Palmers?
- Yeah.
Scrub forward.
- OK.
- Oh. here we go.
Mother and son return from
the trail after about an hour.
They see the flat.
And here goes.
Is that our. uh. tire slasher?
- He circles back.
Looks like
he's offering to help.
So the tire slasher vandalized
the Palmers' vehicle.
then poses as a Good Samaritan
to offer them a ride.
Yeah. plan comes together
for our bad guy.
So this is not just
a missing person's case...
the Palmers were abducted.
Let's see if we can get lucky
and get an ID
with what we got there.
- OK.
Yeah. resolution is too low
for facial rec on the driver.
- What about the car?
- Running the plates.
Stolen.
- Yeah? OK.
NYPD. look into
the stolen vehicle.
- Here's something.
- Hmm?
That Nissan passed a plate
reader 15 minutes ago...
Yeah?
Entering Caleb Smith State Park.
Get a team there now.
♪ ♪
That's the vehicle.
[sighs]
Clear.
Pop the trunk.
♪ ♪
Jubal. we found the sedan.
There's blood in the trunk.
and Troy Palmer's hat.
♪ ♪
Guys.
Looks like we got
a set of boot prints.
♪ ♪
Well. our suspect
could have gone anywhere.
- All right.
What do you want to do. Maggie?
[sighs]
We're going in.
Let's split up.
Stay on your comms.
Go dark.
♪ ♪
[owl hooting]
[birds chirping]
♪ ♪
What's wrong?
I just feel like
I'm being watched here.
[twig snaps]
[suspenseful music]
Suspect is fleeing
south on foot.
I'll try to cut him off.
♪ ♪
FBI!
Scola. Eva.
I've got eyes on the mother.
We're too late.
You see him?
- He's gotta be close by.
We need to set up a cordon.
I need a helo and a K-9.
♪ ♪
We have another body.
young male.
♪ ♪
[door clicks]
Hey.
So the best I can tell.
your victims were killed
in the last 24 hours.
Ligature marks on
their wrists and ankles
suggest they were bound
for several days.
Bodies were washed
with soap and bleach.
so no trace DNA.
and rape kits came back
negative for both.
It's not a lot to go on.
Well. autopsies
were more revealing.
Both mother and son show signs
of organ shrinkage
pointing to starvation.
plus darkening
of the buccal membrane
and poor skin turgor.
classic signs of dehydration.
So he abducted them
and then starved them.
To start with.
You know.
I can email you my report.
- I'm already here.
- Right.
I just figured with what
happened to your sister.
- Thanks. Neil.
Um. it's OK.
I'm good.
Boy was killed quickly.
slit throat.
Mom. not so lucky.
Cause of death.
penetrating sharp-force
injury to the chest.
She was stabbed in the heart?
At least 20 times.
Violent and rageful.
What do you know
about the weapon?
Wounds suggest a nonstandard
profile and thickness.
- A specialty blade?
Or combat. maybe?
Edge geometry's multipurpose.
I think we're looking
more for...
- A dive knife.
- Right.
Actually. how do you know that?
For the same reason I know
I need to get back to the beach.
Thanks.
[tense music]
♪ ♪
No sign of our suspect
since he slipped the cordon
last night. but the cadaver dogs
did hit on
another pair of graves.
Got adult female.
adolescent male.
You were right. Maggie.
You want to tell me
what's going on here?
[camera shutter clicking]
Yeah.
There was a case back in 2002...
a serial killer took 17 lives
before the bureau
caught the guy.
The details match
the Palmer murders.
I mean. from the way
they were tied up.
they were starved. and even
the weapon. a dive knife.
You think this is all connected?
- I do.
- Maggie.
- Give me a sec.
- Yeah.
Hey. Peter. thanks for coming.
What's up?
I don't really know
how to say this.
Just say it.
The South Shore Ripper is back.
Maggie. I caught the Ripper
a long time ago.
and he's dead.
[whistles] Hey. guys.
Dogs got another hit.
♪ ♪
Six new bodies
including the Palmers.
So if the Ripper is dead.
how is he still killing?
♪ ♪
This is the face of pure evil.
Howard James Metcalf.
AKA the South Shore Ripper.
24 years ago.
he terrorized the city.
abducting pairs of victims.
always a mother and a son.
He held them captive.
bound them.
and starved them until
he eventually killed them.
He had evaded capture
for two years.
killing 17 victims
that we know of.
- One victim escaped.
Abel Gaskin.
Goes by Abel Shaw now.
And Abel led us to Metcalf?
No. but when he escaped.
Metcalf got spooked.
He set the home that
he had been holding them in
on fire. destroying any evidence
we could have used against him.
State police were able
to track him down
thanks to the BAU profile.
but Metcalf hanged himself
in his holding cell
that same evening.
So the case
was never adjudicated.
but the killings stopped
after Metcalf's death.
Has to be the guy.
Well. Peter Olsen
was the profiler.
and he thought so.
but now we have
six new victims. same MO.
All we know for certain
is that there is
a killer out there
that has to be stopped.
State police found two graves.
both the same...
middle-aged woman
and young boy.
The most recent set was
killed inside of a month.
The oldest exhibited
advanced decomp
with adipocere formation.
so about five months.
Can you tell us
the cause of death?
The same as the Palmers.
Boys had their throats slit.
Women were stabbed
in the chest repeatedly.
Can you give us
a minute. please?
Yeah.
Come on. tell me you see it.
The victims. the Palmers.
Mothers and sons.
Has to be a copycat.
Valerie Palmer was stabbed
in the heart so many times
that Mosbach said he lost count.
That's overkill.
- Mm-hmm.
Peter. the FBI never
went public with that detail.
and the South Shore Ripper
never made it to trial.
Now. the only way
somebody could recreate
these killings
is if it was the same...
The Ripper hung
himself in his cell.
We arrested him.
He punched his own ticket.
I understand why you'd want
to hold on to that.
What is that supposed to mean?
The only victim to get away
from the Ripper
said you got the wrong guy.
The victim was a 12-year-old boy
who had just seen
his mother murdered.
He was traumatized.
I know.
but what if he could have
led us to a different suspect?
Or an accomplice?
My profile clearly said
one killer. not two.
Then how do you explain this?
All these years later.
we've got new murders
with the same MO.
The Ripper was in it
for the pain.
Once his victims
couldn't feel it anymore.
he tossed the bodies
into a dumpster.
- They were trash to him.
- Precisely.
These new victims were buried.
The MOs are not the same.
It's been 24 years. Peter.
The killer could have evolved.
[dramatic music]
Maybe your theory
needs to as well.
♪ ♪
We've been comparing
the two cases.
Back in 2002. the Ripper
used a standard dive knife.
And the new victims
were killed with the same.
Problem is. these knives
are widely available.
- Right.
What about the gravesite?
ERT find anything usable there?
Negative. but analysis
of the trace fibers
found embedded in the Palmers'
wrists and ankles came in.
It looks like the killer
bound them with
half-inch-diameter rope
featuring
a 12-strand.
double-braid construction
and a unique dye pattern that's
consistent with marine rope.
It's manufactured specifically
by this small company
in Ohio. TideTurner.
It's only sold in three stores
in the tristate area.
All right. let's get
a list over to Eva and Scola.
I want a full report
on anyone who has purchased
that rope in the last year.
I don't want to be
the one to say this.
but if Peter Olsen
got it wrong two decades ago...
Well. then Maggie
will get to the bottom of it.
She and Peter are sitting
with Abel Shaw now.
Look. if this is
the same killer.
maybe the lone survivor
can give us some insight.
I was 12.
and the Ripper held me
and my mom in a basement.
no food. just enough water
to keep us alive for five days.
[solemn music]
[sighs]
Sorry. I try not
to think about it anymore.
Is this really necessary?
I know that this is difficult.
We would not be asking you
if it wasn't important.
- It's OK.
It's OK.
[exhales]
After the third day.
he said that we had to choose
who would live
and who would die.
My mother...
♪ ♪
Uh. she always protected me.
and so she volunteered.
I know that
this is cold comfort.
but. uh. the Ripper
found excitement
breaking down his victims.
Choice was irrelevant.
He was always going
to kill you both.
Then he grabbed the wrong woman.
'cause when he...
started stabbing her...
[gasps]
She fought back and
bought me time to run.
to survive.
After you escaped.
you said that Metcalf
wasn't the man
that killed your mother.
Now. that was 24 years ago.
Do you still believe that now?
- Of course.
Wait. why are you asking?
♪ ♪
He's killing again. isn't he?
Someone is killing. yes. but...
This is your fault.
Abel said you had the wrong guy.
The real killer's been
running free this whole time
because you
wouldn't believe him?
- Erica. it's OK.
- No.
No. none of this is OK.
You know. Abel changed his name
so the real killer
couldn't track him down.
He always could have
contacted the bureau.
We would have helped you.
Oh. so you would have
believed him then?
Erica.
♪ ♪
I miss my mother every day.
Can you tell us anything
about the man that you remember?
I'm sorry.
Even now. the feeling.
it's clear as day.
but my memory is fuzzy.
It has been since I escaped.
Wait.
except the thing from EMDR.
- Yeah.
- It's a therapy used for PTSD.
And it helped.
It also unlocked something
that I had repressed... a smell.
We were starving.
and he would cook every night.
Fish.
And that smell tormented us.
It's probably nothing.
Mm. anything you remember
is helpful.
♪ ♪
So you still think Metcalf
is the Ripper?
The boy experienced
a peritraumatic dissociation.
It's a coping mechanism.
nothing more.
OK. what about the new memory.
the smell of the fish?
I mean. you can't
just ignore that.
[sighs]
Maggie. I wrote
the Ripper's profile.
I knew who we were looking for.
Metcalf checked every box.
[sighs]
Peter. what if...
look. hear me out.
What if you have a blind spot?
OK. what if your ego caused you
to jump the gun
24 years ago and...
Mm-hmm.
Now it's impairing
your judgment?
And what if you just
want me to have erred
so you can fix a failure
of your own?
Wow.
- No. all I'm saying...
- Wow. You know what?
This has nothing
to do with my sister.
All I'm saying is we've
all got blind spots. Maggie.
At BAU. we analyze
hundreds of data points.
from the crime scene
to victimology.
to gain insight on the offender
based on their behavior.
- Behavior.
I know what BAU does.
I also know that profiling
is not a hard science.
Well. it's a proven skill.
fortified by statistics.
OK.
Then look me in the eye
right now
and tell me there is
no statistical chance
that you made a mistake.
[dramatic music]
♪ ♪
You're just gonna leave?
- No. I am going to my car.
I brought my case notes.
and we can go over
all the old suspects again.
[exhales]
♪ ♪
You Jack?
Jack moved to Boca.
It's my shop now.
Can I help you?
- Yeah.
FBI. Special Agents
Ramos and Scola.
Yeah. I made you as Feds
the second you stepped in.
Oh. we were going for fishermen.
Maybe you could help us out.
We're canvassing
some marine supply shops
in the tristate area
as part of an investigation.
and your store popped up
as one of the few
that supplies TideTurner rope.
Ah. don't remind me.
Had to take it off the shelves.
it was such a dud.
You haven't sold any recently?
No. sir.
In fact.
I used my leftover stock
to dress some white-tailed deer
I hunted last fall.
TideTurner might
be crap for boats.
but it's great for
stringing up a carcass.
Well. would you have records
of any customers
who might have purchased
that brand of rope?
[sighs]
I got five years of receipts
downstairs in case
the tax man comes calling.
You're welcome to look.
Sounds good.
[upbeat music playing]
- All right.
Frederick Monk?
- Died in '09.
Stroke.
- OK.
Next. William Hoffman.
Uh. incarcerated in 2014
for aggravated sexual assault
in Santa Cruz.
- Where is he now?
Died in prison last year.
- Nope.
- And he had an IQ of 70.
OK.
All right. let's try
Reggie Kramer with a K.
Hold on.
Kramer dated Mary Vandt?
That's the Ripper's
first victim.
Please.
just forget about Kramer.
- So he's still alive.
Uh. lives in Massapequa.
Says here that he found his own
mother murdered when he was 15.
OK. well. that's
the same age as the boys
the Ripper abducted and killed.
The Ripper was organized.
methodical. fastidious.
When I interviewed Kramer in
2002. his house was a pigsty.
There's absolutely no way.
- Wait.
Hey. guys. there's more.
Kramer owns one of
the bait-and-tackle shops
that Scola and Eva
are canvassing.
- [exhales]
Sales receipts are in
a couple of boxes back there.
[ominous music]
♪ ♪
You ever thought about
tidying up down here a bit?
Yeah. you could digitize.
join the 21st century.
Look.
♪ ♪
[phone ringing]
Maggie.
Hello?
♪ ♪
Service down here is terrible.
Better luck upstairs.
♪ ♪
Yeah. go ahead.
Scola?
Maggie. yeah. what's up?
Hey. we're looking
at the suspects
of the old Ripper case.
and one of the names stood out.
♪ ♪
Those boxes are
just around the corner.
Yeah. keep going.
Yeah.
♪ ♪
His name is Reggie Kramer.
He owns one of the stores
on your list.
- Wait. Kramer?
Kramer?
We're...
we're here now.
♪ ♪
You sharpen your own
knives. Mr. Kramer?
Yeah. just a little something
I like to do to relax.
♪ ♪
You'd like to see my handiwork?
- Drop the knife.
Now.
Hey! Put the knife
on the ground right now.
Slowly.
Keep your hands
where I can see them.
OK. let's all
take a deep breath.
No one has to get hurt.
Now turn around.
Hands behind your back.
♪ ♪
Now I can show you my handiwork.
Five days ago.
Valerie and Troy Palmer
were abducted from a trailhead
just outside of the city.
If you say so.
Suspect matches
your height and your build.
There's a lot of people
on this planet.
And where on this planet were
you five days ago. Mr. Kramer?
Oh. you know. here and there.
- OK.
- I can't say for certain.
Have you ever visited
Caleb Smith State Park?
Oh. many times.
You want to know a secret?
- Sure.
White Pools.
Best fly fishing on
the whole Nissequogue.
- He's toying with them.
- More like a test.
Serial killers are
motivated by domination.
manipulation. and control.
Right. control.
He's cuffed to the table.
He could be hogtied
to the floor.
As far as he's concerned.
he could still win
the chess match.
That is exactly what we want.
Why is that?
It's the only way Maggie
can put him in checkmate.
Your mother. Darlene. died
when you were young. right?
You're being obvious.
Agent Bell.
- How so?
- She was murdered.
You think there's a connection.
Isn't there?
You were 15 years old.
and you were the one
that found the body.
She was in the kitchen.
strangled with her apron.
Rick did it.
- Yeah. your stepfather.
At least that's
what the police said.
You think the police
got the wrong guy?
Do you?
Do you miss her?
Well. she wasn't
a very good mother.
[chuckles]
Well. then again.
I wasn't a very good son.
The thing I find interesting
is you have not once
asked why we brought you in.
Well. I suppose I'm just waiting
for you to show your hand.
OK. here it is.
Three pairs of bodies.
all mothers and sons.
all found in a remote
wilderness wildlife refuge
that you just admitted
to visiting.
And they were tied up with
rope like the one from my shop.
And stabbed to death with
a dive knife like you own.
Murdered in their prime.
just like Mom.
Right again. Reggie.
Maybe they weren't
good mothers or good sons.
Are you the South Shore Ripper?
What do you think?
I just have one more question.
Why these women?
[tense music]
Women like that.
yeah. they would never
be with someone like me.
Oh. they look at me.
and they see a monster.
Well. this monster gave them
what they deserved.
♪ ♪
Start at the beginning.
Whew.
Great work.
I'll let
the Eastern District know
their life just got easier.
- Don't bother.
Kramer's not our killer.
He just wants us
to think that he is.
Hold on.
Are telling me this guy
just took the rap
for six murders
that he didn't commit?
Why would he do that?
- To feel important.
OK. all due respect to
the BAU and its methods.
We're gonna need more than
that to throw out a confession.
Kramer claimed that he was
attracted to his victims.
The rape kits came back
on the Palmers negative.
and nothing in the evidence
supports psychosexual motive.
I think that our killer is
angry and grievance-driven.
OK. fine.
But I am holding Kramer.
Let's keep running down leads.
We've also got
the park ranger. Clyde Bream.
I mean. given the timeline.
he deserves another look.
Bring him in.
Peter.
I don't want to keep
dwelling in the past.
so how do you feel about
building a new profile
with only the current cases?
Sounds good to me.
Good call on Kramer.
All right.
let's begin with victimology.
We know that our current killer
abducts mothers and sons.
He's repetitive. ritualistic.
All six victims are white.
Since serial killers
rarely kill across race.
we can assume he's white too.
The abductions
are clustered near
the hiking trails in this park.
- Mm.
We know he lives in
or around Long Island.
OK.
Crime scene analysis shows
that he is organized.
but not just cleaning
and disposing of the bodies.
He plans the abductions.
the captivity.
It shows patience and maturity.
But he has to be able
to dispose of the bodies.
so we're probably looking for
somebody who's younger than 50.
- Very good.
The signature.
All right. we know
that he deprives his victims
of food and light.
And assuming that
he's giving his new victims
the same impossible choice.
it underscores
his need for power.
Right. power
that he carries through
until he has
an emotional release
where he violently
kills the mother.
But then with the boy.
it's more mechanical.
It's quick.
[sighs]
Peter. everything
we've come up with
just looks like your profile
back in 2002.
Well. I still can't
get around the change
in the postmortem MO.
Because he used to
dump the bodies.
but now he buries them?
- What were you saying before?
Uh. he's evolving. he's...
Yeah. I think
something's changed.
- Mm.
- Mm-hmm.
♪ ♪
[exhales sharply]
It's right in front of us.
What?
Our killer is ritualistic
because he needs to fill
some psychological need. right?
He's working through something.
OK.
He's hiding his self-loathing.
Peter. you were right.
The Ripper is not the killer.
but he's not a copycat either.
Our killer knows
the intimate details
of the Ripper's methods because
he witnessed them firsthand.
Oh. my God.
Yeah. and if you saw
your mother attacked.
wouldn't you be ashamed?
♪ ♪
I don't get it.
Why are you looking
for my husband?
We believe that Abel
has picked up the mantle
for the South Shore Ripper.
- What?
By committing these murders.
he's re-enacting his trauma.
No. that is not possible.
Abel would never do that.
Erica. I know this
is a lot to take in.
but sometimes a killing follows
a precipitating event.
The first pair of murders
happened about five months ago.
So did anything happen
to Abel around that time?
Abel's been stressed.
but... but everyone
would be in our situation.
What's your situation?
I'm pregnant.
The doctor said
it was impossible.
but then we were blessed
with this miracle baby boy.
How did Abel react to that news?
He was nervous.
He's been through so much.
How far along are you?
- [exhales]
A little over five months.
Five months.
We've already
been to your house.
Abel isn't there.
Do you know where
he is right now?
He went fishing.
He stopped going years ago.
but when he found out
he was gonna be a dad.
that's how he's been
blowing off steam.
[tense music]
He's using fishing as a pretext
to abduct another family.
All right. listen up.
Maggie and Peter are convinced
Abel Shaw has already
abducted a new set of victims.
Jubal. it looks like
a mother and son
from Southampton
vanished yesterday.
Audrey and Bryce Cahill.
- Kid's 12.
Fits the bill.
Car was found abandoned
at Rogers Beach near Quogue.
One tire slashed. phones
found smashed down the road.
OK. so this has
gotta be our guy.
Uh. we can't track the Cahills.
Can we track Abel?
Nothing on his phone location.
All right. so we need to do
this the old-fashioned way.
Where could Abel
have taken them?
What do we know about him?
Where does he eat?
Where does he sleep?
What does he do for a living?
Uh. I can help
with the last one.
Abel manages
a significant real estate
portfolio. some commercial.
mostly residential.
So he could be
holding his victims
at one of his properties.
But which one?
Well. I can
cross-reference utilities
against property tax records.
see if any of them are vacant.
- Yeah. do it.
- I might have a shortcut.
OK.
In 2002. the Ripper held
Abel and his mother captive
in the basement of an
abandoned home in East Meadow.
That home was located on
a corner at 1827 Lucille.
OK.
On the night that
the Ripper was caught.
he burned it to the ground.
Years later. someone else
bought the lot
and built a new home on it.
Only this time. the front door
was facing the adjacent street.
Same exact property
has a new address.
and guess who owns it now.
- Abel Shaw?
Yes. as Abel Gaskin.
It's the only property
still registered
under his birth name.
If Abel is trying to recreate
the Ripper's crimes...
It makes sense he would
use the same kill box.
Get Maggie on the line.
So we found his kill box.
so now what?
Are we gonna breach and arrest?
- No. it's way too risky.
Abel's capture phase
lasts about five days.
They could still be alive.
Thank you.
We're certainly not sitting
around. though. either.
No. the team did a trash cover
and discovered that he uses
a seafood delivery service.
Right. so he cooks food
to taunt his victims.
just like the original Ripper.
- Yeah.
They're making a delivery
to the house in an hour.
That's our in.
♪ ♪
[doorbell rings]
- That's him.
Hit it.
[explosion]
- [grunts]
[suspenseful music]
♪ ♪
[both grunting]
OK. go downstairs
and check the basement.
I got him.
♪ ♪
- Ready?
- Yeah.
Audrey?
Bryce?
[tense music]
We're too late.
♪ ♪
- Maggie.
- Yeah?
No Cahills in the basement.
Where are they?
Did you kill them?
Why would I do that?
They haven't chosen yet.
♪ ♪
SWAT raided every property
in Abel's portfolio.
Still no sign of the Cahills.
If they are still alive.
he's gotta tell us
where he's moved them.
- Well. that'll be tough.
He's fixated on them
completing the ritual.
Abel's compulsions are motivated
by his shame and remorse.
So why don't we confront him?
Use that against him.
- Do it.
- You coming?
- No.
You saw Abel
for who he really is.
It's your case now.
[door buzzes]
- Guess what. Abel.
You washed the bodies.
You didn't clean the basement.
ERT found prints and DNA.
We're gonna tie you
to all six murders.
and the only way that you can
help yourself at this point
is by telling me where you're
hiding Audrey and Bryce Cahill.
It's over.
You can't hurt them anymore.
I've been studying
your patterns. Abel.
All you're doing is repeating
what happened to you
when you let your mother die.
Well. except you did
wash the bodies.
then you laid them to rest.
You know what that tells me?
It tells me that you're ashamed.
that you're remorseful.
You don't know what
you're talking about.
[tense music]
You still have a chance
to save Audrey and Bryce
and redeem yourself.
Be the hero that you wanted
to be all those years ago.
♪ ♪
Tell me where they are.
[breathes deeply]
♪ ♪
Not until they choose.
I thought he was supposed
to be remorseful.
I'm no longer sure
abandoning his mother
is the root of his shame.
How are we supposed to know
what the root is?
Well. Maggie will have to
reprofile him on the fly.
It is over.
- No. it isn't.
- Well. how do you figure?
I mean. short of putting the
knife in Bryce's hand yourself.
♪ ♪
There was a second choice
that day.
The Ripper put the knife
in your hand
and gave you the choice...
you kill your mother.
or he's gonna kill you both.
♪ ♪
None of the other kids
could pull it off.
They couldn't go
through with it.
but you were different.
You made the choice
to kill your own mother.
♪ ♪
That's why Metcalf let you go.
because he saw you
for who you really are.
You're a killer. just like him.
- Don't.
And you didn't want
to identify him.
because you didn't want
everyone else
to know your shame.
- Shut up. Shut up. OK?
I mean. when he died
you must have thought
this was all done. right?
You could just put it
all behind you?
♪ ♪
Till your wife got pregnant.
That wasn't supposed to happen.
So when she comes to tell you
that she's gonna
have this miracle baby.
a baby boy. you panicked.
I panicked.
I mean. why wouldn't you?
What if this precious baby
is like you?
Broken?
- I'm not broken.
You have made
all of these people
live your exact nightmare
for one thing alone.
You wanted to find
one other person
who made the same choice as you.
so that you wouldn't feel alone.
[sniffles]
I can free them.
I can free them from the lies
that they tell themselves
about who they really are.
No. Nobody else
has made that choice.
and nobody's going to.
Not even Bryce.
You don't know that.
- I know.
- No.
- Yes.
And you know what?
I think deep down.
you know that too.
You weren't there.
You didn't see the look
on that kid's face
when I gave him the knife.
He's gonna do it.
He swore he would do it.
I bet he already has.
You don't tell us
where they are.
how are you ever
gonna know for sure?
♪ ♪
Checkmate.
[suspenseful music]
♪ ♪
- Go around the sides.
- Yep.
It's locked. Scola.
[glass shatters]
♪ ♪
Pull it!
Oh. my God.
OK.
♪ ♪
Give me a hand.
Bryce.
Come on.
Hey. wake up. Bryce.
♪ ♪
I've got a pulse.
It's faint. but she's alive.
- Your mom's gonna be OK.
So are you.
- I... I didn't do it.
I couldn't.
[dramatic music]
♪ ♪
[siren blares]
- Hey.
Look. uh. a couple of things
I said back there...
No. no.
I'm the one who needs
to apologize.
Your original profile
was spot-on.
and I shouldn't have pushed...
- Oh. no. no. no. no. no.
You were right in the end.
I missed some things.
You sensed them. and
you never stopped questioning.
You know. ever since
Erin died. I've...
I've been trying to
separate what happened
to her with what I do.
Mm-hmm.
I can't.
I don't think
I'll ever be able to.
So I'm choosing to use it as
an edge to save whoever I can.
[gentle music]
You once told me that
you no longer recognize
the world around you.
But I think you see
the world exactly
for what it is.
all the bad and all the good.
and you just refuse
to give up on it.
And. uh. well...
[chuckles]
I'm lucky to know you. Maggie.
♪ ♪
Thank you.
See you around.
♪ ♪
[wolf howls]